Guide to the College of Education Records
University of Houston Libraries
College of Education Records
1940-2009
2009-010
University of Houston. College of Education
2.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
These records contain 6 boxes relating to the College of Education at the University of Houston. A significant portion of this material was given to the archives from the university Print Plant.
Historical Note:
The College of Education was established in 1942. During WWII, the college had a vital wartime assignment recruiting and retraining teachers to take the places of the hundreds who left the profession for high-paying jobs in the war industry or for the armed services. Former teachers, particularly women, were urged to seek recertification, primarily through a unique Education Workshop. [1] In 1945, the School of Education was expanded to offer the degree of Doctor in Education. [2]
Farish Hall, dedicated in 1975, is the current location of the College of Education. A large endowment from Mrs. Stephen Power Farish was given to name the College of Education Building for her husband, a former UH regent. [3]
he College of Education works to shape and staff educational systems that are responsive to our rapidly changing society. The college prepares teachers, counselors, psychologists, school and higher education administrators and professionals for a variety of educational settings, including work in social agencies, medical facilities, businesses, and government posts. The college offers students both a broad range of innovative programs and the opportunity to learn about recent developments in educational practice and thought. The university's urban setting also offers students the opportunity to work with learners in a variety of settings.
The College of Education is home to four academic departments - Curriculum and Instruction, Educational Leadership and Cultural Studies, Educational Psychology, and Health and Human Performance - and several centers and institutes.
Refernces:
[1] Patrick J. Nicholson, In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston (Houston, TX: Pacesetter Press, 1977), 219-220.
[2] Patrick J. Nicholson, In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston (Houston, TX: Pacesetter Press, 1977), 267.
[3] Patrick J. Nicholson, In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston (Houston, TX: Pacesetter Press, 1977), 458.
[4] About, available from www.coe.uh.edu. 12 August 2009.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. College of Education.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
These records contain 6 boxes relating to the College of Education at the University of Houston. A significant portion of this material was given to the archives from the university Print Plant. Materials include course information, workshop flyers, research papers, instructional materials, event flyers, correspondence, certificates, newsletters, teaching programs. Included in this collection is a Publications series that includes faculty studies, and administrative reports. This collection is arranged chronologically and alphabetically as necessary. Materials range in date from the 1940s to 2009.
Detailed List of Contents
- Printed materials arranged by date
  - 1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - 1960s (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - 1970s (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - 1980s (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - 1980s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1990s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 2000s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stationery, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - undated (Box 2, Folder 5-10)
- Publications
  - Faculty Directory, undated (A few of the faculty members listed here can also be found in the Faculty Vita Collection.) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Accreditation Report to National Council for Accreditation; 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bureau of Education and Research Services; Publications; Administrative Function in a Climate of Change: a Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bureau of Education and Research Services; Publications; Chambers County School Survey; 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bureau of Education and Research Services; Publications; Educational Specifications; 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bureau of Education and Research Services; Publications; The Effects of Group Guidance Upon the Self-Esteem…; 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bureau of Education and Research Services; Publications; "Educational Specifications Hull- Daisetta High School Liberty County, Texas (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bureau of Education and Research Services; Publications; Research and Service Series; "The Effects of Group Guidance upon the self esteem, interpersonal relationships, and Educational Achievement of the culturally different child", 1969 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - College of Education Bureau of Education Research and Services: "Elementary Education Series" "Why?", August, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bureau of Education Research and Services Publications "Research and Service Series" "Modern Mathematics: A problem in Professional Retraining", August, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - CBTE Program, Publications "The curruculum component Module", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Center for Gifted and Talented Publications "Graduate Research Monographs", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - College of Education Foundation; Annual Reports, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Conferences "Accommodating The Exceptional child in the regular classroom" (Dodds Mediterranean Workshop) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Conferences; "Chemicals and The Environment and Institute for Science Teachers", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Department of Administration and Supervision; Application for Membership to University Council (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Department of Administration and Supervision; Conferences; Personnel Management Goals in Education; 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Department of Curriculum and Instruction; Publications; An Introductory Module to Individualized Science Instructional System (ISIS) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Department of Curriculum and Instruction; Publications; Helping Students Master Subject Matter; 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Department of Curriculum and Instruction; Student Publication; Student Research Report; 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Directed Teaching Program; Publications; Handbook for Cooperating Teachers; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Directed Teaching Program; Publications; Handbook for Student Teachers; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Reports; Faculty Vitae: Self-Study Report of the College of Education; 1982 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Reports; N.C.A.T.E. Accreditation Self-Study Report; 1982 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Reports; Planning for Program Excellence; 1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Studies; An Investigation into Factors Which Reinforce or Deter Creativity in Children; 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Studies; Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development; Labs; 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Studies; Effects of Visual and Auditory Background on Reading Achievement; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Faculty Studies; Follow Up Study of the Effects of a Language Stimulation Program; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Studies; Handbook for the Development of Instructional Modules; 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Faculty Studies; Helping Exceptional Learners Progress (HELP); 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Faculty Studies; Philosophy and Classroom Practice: the Nederland Study; 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Faculty Studies; Project: Data/Use (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Faculty Studies; Proposal for an Eighth Cycle Teacher Corps Program; 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Studies; School Plant Research and Planning Information Abstract Service; 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Faculty Studies; Teaching in a Multicultural Society (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Faculty Studies; Using Information for ERIC to Solve Educational Problems; 1981 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Faculty Studies; Validation of a Carefulness Test Battery Against Training School Criteria; 1964 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Foundations of Education Department; Publications; Developmental Characteristics of Sixth Grade Children 1965 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Foundations of Education Department; Publications; Using Community Resources Within the Curriculum; 1960 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Restructuring Teacher Education; 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 2.0: Awareness in Relation to Others; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 3.0: Sharing Self with Others; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 4.0: Communication: Listening and Responding; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 5.0: Communication Nonverbal; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 6.0: Communication: One-Way and Two-Way; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 7.0: Decision Making I; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 8.0: Decision Making II; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 9.0: Decision Making III; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 10.0: Effective Problem Solving; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 11.0: Teacher Interaction; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 12.0: Professional Ethics for the Educator; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 13.0: Group Process; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Affective 14.0: Verbal Interaction; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Analysis of Learning Example: “Disadvantaged Learners”; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Book Abstracts; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; CBTE: Proficiency Analysis Rating; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Educational Decision Making; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Generic Competencies: Secondary; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Prospectus for Language Arts; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Psychological Foundations I: 1.0 Types of Learning; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Psychological Foundation I: 2.0 Operant Conditioning; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Psychological Foundation II: Phenomenological Learning; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Psychological Foundation II: Piaget and Education; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Psychological Foundations II: 1.2 Intelligence; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Science Methods Component: Module 1.0 Inquiry Skills, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Social Studies Methods Component: Social Studies Curriculum Materials; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural I; 1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural II; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural III: Organizational Climate; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural 3.0: School Law; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural Foundations 1.0: Groups and Attitudes; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural Foundations: 4.0 Family, Community, School (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Socio-Cultural Foundations: Groups and Achievement 2.0; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Modules 1.0-3.0; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Module 4.0: Identifying Higher Order Questions; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Module 5.0: Asking Higher Order Questions; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Module 6.0: Using Set Induction; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Module 7.0: Stimulus Variations; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Module 8.0: Using Reinforcement Techniques; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I; Module 9.0: Nonverbal Mannerisms; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching I: Module 10.0: Demonstrating Legible Handwriting; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching II; Module 11.0: Communication and Attending Behavior; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching II; Module 12.0: Using Probing Questions; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching II; Module 13.0: Using Divergent Questions; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching II; Module 14.0: Analysis of Teaching Behavior; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching II; Module 15.0: Classroom Management; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Houston Competency-Based Teacher Center; Publications; Competency-Based Teacher Education; Teaching III; Module 17.0: Accountability; 1972 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Institutional Report Prepared for National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education (vol. 1); 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; A Look at Values; 1974 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Classroom Climate; 1974 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Establishing Instructional Set; 1973 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Facilitating Cognitive Closure; 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Professional Development Center; Federal Role in School Reform from Sociological and Educational Perspectives (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Inquiry Approach; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Instructional Media; 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Managing Defiant Behavior; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Recipe of Classroom Ideas; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Self and Others; 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Self-Concept; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Strategies for Professional Growth; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Systems Approach to Instructional Design; 1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Professional Development Center; Publications; Professional Development Modules; Teacher Self-Evaluation; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Program Guides; Doctoral Policies, Procedures and Program Guide; 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Program Guides; Program Guide for Master Students; 1986, 1995, 2000, 2002, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Program Guides; Thesis and Dissertation Guide (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Program Guides; Thesis and Dissertation Guide (2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Program Reports; Department of Educational Leadership and Cultural Studies; Institutional Self-Evaluation of the Doctoral Program in Administration and Supervision; 1982 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Publications; Analyzing Videotaped Physical Science Demonstrations and Laboratories; 1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Publications; Bibliography on Teacher Aides; 1967 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Publications; C and I Secondary (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Publications; Helping the Learning Disabled; 1977 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Publications; the Maryland Diagnostic Arithmetic Test and Interview Protocols; 1976 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Publications; Mathematics in the Elementary School; 1972 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Publications; Multicultural Education: A Sourcebook for Educators; 1979 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Publications; Teaching Reading Modules (4th ed.); 1974 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Publications; Teaching Reading Modules; 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Publications; Teaching Science in the Elementary Schools; 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Self-Studies; Self-Study Report of the College of Education; 1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Texas Education Agency Evaluation; 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)